<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The barren trees doome a sermon preached at Newbery on the fifth day of August. Beeing the day of his Maiesties most happy deliuerance from the bloudy conspiracie of the Earle of Gowry and his brother Alexander. By Bartholomevv Parsons Batchelour in Diuinitie, and vicar of Collingborne Kingstone in the countie of Wiltes.</title>
            <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1616</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09052</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 19344</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114079</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99849307</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99849307</idno>
            <idno type="VID">14447</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09052)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 14447)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 682:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The barren trees doome a sermon preached at Newbery on the fifth day of August. Beeing the day of his Maiesties most happy deliuerance from the bloudy conspiracie of the Earle of Gowry and his brother Alexander. By Bartholomevv Parsons Batchelour in Diuinitie, and vicar of Collingborne Kingstone in the countie of Wiltes.</title>
                  <author>Parsons, Bartholomew, 1574-1642.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 32, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, for Mathevv Lavv, and are to be sold at his shop in Pauls Church-yard at the signe of the Fox,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1616.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:14447:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE BARREN TREES DOOME: <hi>A SERMON</hi> PREA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CHED AT NEWBERY ON THE FIFTH DAY OF AVGVST.</p>
            <p>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>E DAY OF HIS <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> MOST HAPPY DE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>m THE BLOVDY CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracie of the Earle of Gowry and his brother <hi>Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By BARTHOLOMEVV PARSONS Batchelour in Diuinitie, and Vicar of Collingborne <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone in the Countie of Wiltes.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DAN. 4.23.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Hew downe the Tree and deſtroy it.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 18.40.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Thou haſt giuen me the neckes of mine enemies, that I might deſtroy them that hate me.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by NICHOLAS OKES, for MATHEVV LAVV, and are to be ſold at his ſhop in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church-yard at the ſigne of the Fox. 1616.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:14447:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:14447:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE WIL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LIAM EARLE OF PENBROOKE, LORD HARBERT OF CARDIFFE LORD <hi>Parr</hi> and <hi>Roſſe</hi> of <hi>Kendall,</hi> Lord <hi>Marmion</hi> and S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Quintine,</hi> Lord Chamberlaine to his Maieſty, Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the Garter, and one of his Maieſties <hi>moſt Honourable Priuy Councell.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>ING <hi>Saul</hi> being brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch a ſtraight, that to eſcape the hands of the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed Philiſtimes, hee laid violent hands vpon himſelfe, fell vpon his owne ſword and died <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 31.4.</note>. <hi>Dauid</hi> in his Funerall Elegies, in his Lamentations wherewith hee lamented ouer <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Ionathan,</hi> cryeth out, <hi>Tell it not in Gath, publiſh it not in the ſtreets of Aſhkelon, leſt the daughters of the Philiſtims reioyce, leſt the daughters of the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>circumciſed tryumph</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">2. Sam. 1.20.</note>. But when a better then
<pb facs="tcp:14447:3"/>
               <hi>Saul</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">1. Sam. 15.28.</note>, to whom God hath giuen the Kingdomes of great Brittaine, being ſo brought into the ſnare of thoſe mightie Hunters, <hi>Nimrods,</hi> vncircumciſed in heart, the Earle of <hi>Gowry</hi> and his brethren, that the ſorrowes of death compaſſed him, the floods of the vngodly made him afraid <note n="d" place="margin">Pſalm. 18.4.</note>, and hee was ready to ſay with King <hi>Hezekiah, I am depriued of the reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due of my yeares, I ſhall not ſee the Lord in the Land of the liuing, I ſhall behold man no more with the Inhabitants of the world</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Eſa. 38.10.11</note>, was notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding ſo deliuered out of the ſnare of thoſe Fow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, that not an haire of his head fell to the ground; It is a good thing for vs that are the Lords <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cones</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 58.1.</note>, in our Panygyrickes that wee ſpeake vnto the Lord in the day of the commemoration thereof <note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 18.1.</note>, to cry it in the ſtreetes, in the chiefe places of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, in the opening of the gates <note n="h" place="margin">Prou. 1.20.</note>, and in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Lord that both Sion hearing of it, may reioyce and be glad <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 96.8.</note>; and all the daughters of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon that beare euill will at Sion, all treacherous <hi>Zi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bahs,</hi> that could find in heart to blow the Trumpet of rebellion againſt their Soueraignes <note n="k" place="margin">2 Sam. 20.1.</note>, may bee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded, and hang downe their heads for ſhame. Now though my tongue be not as the pen of a ready writer, though mine hand want <hi>Apelles</hi> Art to paint out this our <hi>Alexander</hi> in his great deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; yet I haue made bold, in mine heart to endite ſome good matter, with my tongue to ſpeake, and with my pen to publiſh the things that I haue made touching the King <note n="l" place="margin">Pſalm. 45.1.</note> And albeit it might be ſaid to mee, being little both in mine owne and others eyes,
<pb facs="tcp:14447:3"/>What art thou? Whence commeſt thou? yet I haue like <hi>Heſter,</hi> aduentured to come <hi>w<hi rend="sup">th</hi>
               </hi> theſe my raw medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations into the Courts of your Honors houſe without calling thither <note n="m" place="margin">Heſt. 4.10.</note>, hoping as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſhewed kindnes to <hi>Mephiboſheth</hi> for <hi>Ionathans</hi> ſake <note n="n" place="margin">2. Sam. 9.7.</note>, ſo you will vouch ſafe to receaue it into your fauourable protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on for the ſubiects ſake whereof it intreateth, his Highneſſe happy and wonderfull ſauing, in whoſe ſafety at that time conſiſted, both in generall, the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of theſe two famous kingdomes, and alſo in ſpeciall, the continuance of your honours proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and dignitie vnto this day; you being one of the foules of the aire that haue their habitation in the branches of this great tree <note n="o" place="margin">Dan. 4 21.</note>. Againe, my perſwaſions are ſtrong, that any thing ſpoken of his Maieſties wonderfull deliuerance, ſhall be welcome to him, in whom haue bene obſerued to meet, and be conioyned, thoſe ſeuerall commendations that <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great gaue to two of his ſeruants, commending the one <hi>(Craterus)</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a louer of the king in the things that concerned his crowne and dignitie: the other <hi>(Hephaeſtion)</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a louer of <hi>Alexander</hi> in a priuate reſpect &amp; affection towards his perſon: and that the baſeſt earthen veſſell, that bringeth in it any of the heauenly treaſures, ſhall finde fauour in his eyes, who (as it was ſayd of <hi>Sce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uola</hi> that he was <hi>Iuriſperitorum eloquentiſſimus,</hi> of all the Lawyers the moſt eloquent man) is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, of our Nobles the moſt skilfull in Diuinitie, who hath made Gods teſtimonies his counſellers, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth more delight in them then in thouſands of gold
<pb facs="tcp:14447:4"/>and ſiluer, and thinketh it a greater honour to bee a member of the Church, then a Peere of the Realme. All which hath made me put on the ſpirit of bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, to dedicate vnto your honorable protection, this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſong of triumph, wherein the higheſt note is concerning the Mercies of the Lord, and the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe that he hath ſhewed vnto our <hi>Dauid</hi> his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. Pardon then (I beſeech your Honour) my boldneſſe, accept it with gracious fauour, and protect it vnder the ſhadow of your roofe (as <hi>Lot</hi> did the Angels) that miſcreants may doe nothing vnto it. And in my poore meaſure I wil not ceaſe to fall down an humble ſuppliant before the Throne of grace, to make requeſt, that God which hath bleſſed you with the bleſsings of heauen aboue, and of the deepe that lyeth vnder neath, would alſo bleſſe you with all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall bleſsings in heauenly things in Chriſt; who hath giuen you a name vpon earth, would giue you a name and place within his houſe and his walles; which hath made you happy in ſtanding before an earthly <hi>Salomon,</hi> would giue you the fulneſſe of ioy in his preſence; and which hath ſet you with the Princes of his people, would in his good time ſet you at his right hand where there are pleaſures for euermore.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours in all humble duty, BARTHOLOMEVV PARSONS.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:14447:4"/>
            <head>THE BARREN TREES DOOME.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>MATH. 3.10.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Therefore euery Tree which bringeth not forth good fruite, is hewen downe, and caſt into the fire.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HAT this Parabolicall ſpeech may not bee vttered to vs, as vnto them to <hi>whom it is not giuen to know the ſecrets of the Kingdome of heauen: Who ſeeing do not ſee, and hearing doe not heare, nor vnderſtand</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Mat. 13.11.</note>: If with the Diſciples wee aske the heauenly Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter apart concerning this Parable, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hee will vnfold and expound it vnto vs <note n="b" place="margin">Mar. 4.34.</note>: And as hee doth, <hi>aperire os ſuum in parabolis,</hi> open his mouth in Parables; ſo hee will, <hi>aperire etiam ipſas parabolas,</hi> open the Parables them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:14447:5"/>alſo <note n="c" place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. <hi>77.</hi>
               </note>, if wee conſult with the heauenly Oracles, the light of them will diſpell the darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that hangeth on the face of this Text: <hi>Nihil enim fere, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Auguſt. de doctr. Chriſt. l. <hi>2.</hi> cap. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>) For the moſt part there is nothing fetched out of thoſe obſcurities (which are in the Scriptures) which we may not finde more plainly ſpoken in another place. Let vs know then, that the Lord (who ſpeaketh of himſelfe according to the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew prouerbe, <hi>With the tongues of the ſonnes of men,</hi> and of whom, according to that golden rule of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> thoſe things which in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, are ſpoken according to humane affection, are to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood as becommeth the nature of God) is plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to take vpon him the name and profeſſion of an Husbandman, whoſe husbandry his Saints are <note n="e" place="margin">1. Cor. 3.9.</note>: Of a Maiſter: Of a Vineyard, <note n="f" place="margin">Eſay 5.1.</note> whoſe Vineyard is the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the men of <hi>Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dah</hi> his Plants <note n="g" place="margin">Ibid. v. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note>, being a Vine, noble for gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity <note n="h" place="margin">Ierem. 2.21.</note>, excellent for glory <note n="i" place="margin">Ezek. 17.8.</note>, and pleaſant for delectation <note n="k" place="margin">Eſay 5.7.</note>: And of a Gardener, whoſe Spouſe is a Garden incloſed, the Plants where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are an Orchard of Pomegranats with plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant Fruite <note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 4.12.</note>. Now as in the floare of the Church, there is mingled together, chaffe to be ſeuered with the fanne and throwne into the fire, and wheate to bee gathered into the Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner <note n="m" place="margin">Math. 3.12.</note>; In the field of the Kingdome of Heauen, are tares to bee pulled out, and burnt vp, and wheate to bee carryed into the Barne in their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:14447:5"/>due ſeaſon <note n="n" place="margin">Math. 13 30.</note>: In the Net of the Kingdome of Heauen, are gathered all kinds of things; bad to bee caſt away, and good to bee put into veſſels <note n="o" place="margin">Math. 13.44.48.</note>.</p>
            <p>So in this Vineyard of the Lords of Hoſts, in this garden of our Wel-beloued, there are found, both trees planted by the riuers of the water of the Sanctuary, whoſe leaues ſhall not fade, neither ſhall their fruite faile <note n="p" place="margin">Ezek. 47.12.</note>; and alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Trees of Autumne</hi> decaying, whoſe fruite withereth; yea without fruite, <hi>twiſe dead,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Iude 12.</note> as the ſpeech of the Holy Ghoſt riſeth by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees in that place. Theſe, theſe Trees doth this Meſſenger before the face of the Lord, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing like to purging fire <note n="r" place="margin">Mal. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>De coelo tangere,</hi> ſtrike at from heauen; and not either <hi>Totum genus hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum,</hi> all man-kind (as ſome Interpreters would haue it <note n="ſ" place="margin">Hugo Cardin. Beda Ianſen.</note>) for they are the Trees of the Forreſts <note n="t" place="margin">Eſay 44.14.</note>, not of the Garden of the Lord: or onely <hi>Genus Iſraeliticum,</hi> the people of Iſrael (as ſome reſtraine this commination <note n="u" place="margin">Chryſ. Hilar. Theophilact. Muſcul. Piſcat. Maldon.</note>.) For though this Parabolicall ſpeech be ſpecially in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt euill Profeſſours of his time by <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt heere, as it is vſed alſo by our Sauiour againſt euill Prophets of the ſuccee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding times <note n="x" place="margin">Math. 7.19.</note>; yet <hi>Communi ratione,</hi> in a generall conſideration all <hi>Pſeudo-Chriſtians,</hi> that like the Angel of the Church in <hi>Sardis</hi> haue a name that they liue, but are dead <note n="y" place="margin">Reu. 3.1.</note>, are vnderſtood; inclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding herein; who bearing not fruite in Chriſt, muſt be taken away <note n="z" place="margin">Iohn 15.2.</note>, and being barren, muſt be
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:14447:6"/>cut vp, that they may not cumber the ground of Gods Sanctuary <note n="a" place="margin">Luke 13.7.</note>. Of which Trees, not to the boughes or body, but to the roote, is laid alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, not to be laid hereafter; not a knife to prune (for ſuch dreſſing is requiſite for the good bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches that bring forth fruit <note n="b" place="margin">Iohn 15.2.</note>) but an axe to cut downe: Which whether wee enterprete with Saint <hi>Ierome</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Hieron. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> of the Miniſtery of that moſt pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing <note n="d" place="margin">Heb. 4.12.</note> word, which is like as a fire, and like an hammer breaking the Rockes <note n="e" place="margin">Ier. 23.29.</note>, and which by denouncing vengeance againſt all diſobedience, doth plucke vp, roote out, deſtroy and throw downe <note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 1.10.</note> (for ſo God heweth by his Prophets, and ſlayeth by the words of his Mouth <note n="g" place="margin">Hoſ. 6.5.</note>:) Or with <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">Chriſ. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note>, to bee the <hi>Acutiſsima ira con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummationis,</hi> Gods moſt ſharpe anger that will make an end of all: With <hi>Maldonate,</hi> the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinum Iudicium,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Maldonat. in locum.</note> diuine iudgement; It commeth all to one, there being but little difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene Gods voyce threatning, and his hand taking vengeance on them. <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> ſummeth vp the whole hitherto very elegantly, <hi>Nihil ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribilius, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Chriſ. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum.</note> There is nothing more more ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible then this manner of ſpeaking, for hee threatneth not them with a flying hooke, nor with the deſtruction of the hedge, nor the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding downe of the Vineyard, but with a cutting Axe; yea, and which is more terrible, with ſuch an Axe that is at hand, and cutteth euen pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore] Nihil certius,</hi> nothing is more
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:14447:6"/>certaine, it is a concluſion from the breathe of his mouth, who is the God that cannot lie <note n="l" place="margin">Tit. 1.2.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Tree]</hi> yea a Tree of the Vineyard, of the Garden, that no man may build vpon, or boaſt of a plantation without fructification.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Euery Tree]</hi> that no man may exempt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe from the common condition; For hee that goeth about to except himſelfe doth but deceiue himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That bringeth not forth good fruit]</hi> that no man may thinke it enough to haue brought forth good fruite, <note n="m" place="margin">Maldonat in locum.</note> nor place the whole duty of a Chriſtian in abſtayning from euill.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Is cut downe]</hi> not, <hi>ſhall be cut downe:</hi> the time preſent, intimating the preſentneſſe of the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; and hee threatneth not any ſlight ſtroke, but cutting downe by all meanes <note n="n" place="margin">Muſculus in locum.</note>.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And caſt into the fire]</hi> that like <hi>Iudas</hi> it might go into his owne place <note n="o" place="margin">Acts 1.25.</note>.</p>
            <p>This ſecond <hi>Elias</hi> then walking in the ſpirit and power of the firſt <hi>Elias,</hi> doth, as it were, call for fire from heauen <note n="p" place="margin">2. King. 1.10.</note> againſt theſe barren vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing Trees, that haue loſt the bleſſing of their creation in Chriſt Ieſus <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 1.11. Epheſ. 2.10.</note>, to bring forth fruite according to their kinde.</p>
            <p>But that we may take a ſuruay of the particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars in their rankes, let vs marke,</p>
            <p>Firſt, the certainty of the vengeance denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced; <hi>Therefore,]</hi> It is not a matter nakedly affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, but ſtrongly concluded, like the Apoſtles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <note n="r" place="margin">Rom. 3.28</note> 
               <hi>We conclude, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:14447:7"/>
Secondly, the ſubiect, or perſon, capable of this puniſhment; <hi>A Tree</hi>] of the garden; which leaſt the Iudge ſhould ſhew himſelfe partiall, is amplified by the generall extent, <hi>euery</hi> ſuch <hi>Tree.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the mouing cauſe hereof; For <hi>farre be it from the Iudge of the whole world that hee ſhould not do right,</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 18.25.</note> that he ſhould puniſh any vndeſeruedly; becauſe <hi>it bringeth not forth good fruite.</hi>]</p>
            <p>Laſtly, the nature of the puniſhment ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vpon two feete:</p>
            <list>
               <item>1 Such a Tree is to be <hi>Hewne downe</hi>] that it may not cumber the ground, and offend other good plants.</item>
               <item>2 It muſt be <hi>caſt into the fire</hi>] that it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue as it hath deſerued, for the end of ſuch Trees is to be burned <note n="t" place="margin">Hebr. 6.8.</note>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>The certainty of the vengeance heere de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, ſtandeth in the doore of the Text, like <hi>Abraham</hi> in the dore of his Tent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore:</hi>] It is not a bare affirmation, which were enough, but a demonſtratiue concluſion, inferred out of his premiſſes, which is, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſuperaboundant:</hi> For if the words of Gods mouth are mighty and operatiue, <hi>Dixit, &amp; facta ſunt;</hi>
               <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 33.9.</note> much more are the counſels of his heart infallible, indiuertible, <hi>The counſell of the Lord ſtandeth for euer, the thoughts of his heart to all generations</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">Ibid. verſ. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note>: Therefore (as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith well) <hi>If we beleeue not God when hee ſpeaketh, yet
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:14447:7"/>let vs beleeue him when hee ſweareth:</hi> So, if we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue not God when hee doth nakedly Affirme, yet let there be a <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a full aſſurance of faith in vs, when hee doth regularly Conclude, and compell vs (as it were) by force of Argument. As then all the promiſes of God, are <hi>Yea and amen, in Chriſt Ieſus: I will not</hi> (ſaith hee <note n="y" place="margin">2. Cor. 1.20.</note>) <hi>fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſify my truth, I will not alter the thing that is gone out of my lips</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 89.33.</note>: So all his denunciations of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance are ſtable, yea immutable, as the Lawes of the <hi>Medes</hi> and <hi>Perſians,</hi> which alter not <note n="a" place="margin">Dan. 6.8.</note>. <hi>Moriendo morieris, Thou ſhalt ſurely die the death</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Gen. 2.17.</note>, was <hi>Adams</hi> doome, if hee ſhould fall into ſinne; the words being doubled, becauſe the thing was eſtabliſhed, as in <hi>Pharoahs</hi> dreame <note n="c" place="margin">Gen. 41.32</note>: Whether vengeance then come in the morning, as vpon the <hi>Sodomites</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Gen. 19.23.24.</note>, vpon whom about the riſing of the Sunne <hi>Gehennam è coelo miſit deus</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">Saluianus l. <hi>1</hi> de gubernat dei.</note>, God ſent an hell out of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen; Or at noone day, as to <hi>Haman,</hi> who was caught from his dinner to the gallowes <note n="f" place="margin">Eſter 7.9.</note>; Or at euentide, as to <hi>Ahab,</hi> who being wounded in warre, dyed in his Chariot about the going downe of the Sunne <note n="g" place="margin">1. King. 22 35</note>: Or in the night ſeaſon, as to <hi>Chedorlaomer,</hi> and the Kings that were with him, whom <hi>Abraham</hi> ouertooke and ſmote by night <note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 14.15.</note>: Whether it come <hi>ſerius aut citiùs,</hi> later or ſooner, yet <hi>certis paſsibus illa venit,</hi> it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſurely without failing: <hi>The Lord that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenceth will ſurely recompence</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Ier. 51.56.</note> 
               <hi>Know certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that yee ſhall die by the ſword, by the famine and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:14447:8"/>by the peſtilence</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Ier. 42.22.</note>. And that viſion that <hi>Habecuck</hi> ſaw againſt the capitall ſinnes, not onely of his times, but alſo of all times; <hi>Pride, Couetouſneſſe, drunkennes, and Idolatry,</hi> muſt ſurely come <note n="l" place="margin">Habacuk. 2.3</note>. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not ſo much for the ſecreſie, as for the cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty thereof, is vengeance ſealed vp amongſt Gods treaſures, <note n="m" place="margin">Deut. 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 34.</note> yea bound with the indiſſoluble band of an oath; <hi>The Lord ſweareth that hee will haue warre with Amalecke from generation to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Exod. 17.16.</note>: <hi>I haue ſworne vnto the houſe of</hi> Eli, <hi>that the iniquity of</hi> Elies <hi>houſe ſhall not be purged with ſacrifice, nor offering for euer</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">1. Sam. 3.14.</note> Let no man then, when hee heareth the words of Gods cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes denounced againſt his euill waies, ſing a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiem</hi> to his owne ſoule, bleſſe himſelfe in his heart, ſaying, with the ſtubborne in heart, <hi>I ſhall haue peace, though I walke according to the ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſſe of mine heart</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Deut. 29.19.</note>; with the wicked, <hi>I ſhall neuer be moued</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Pſalme 10.6.</note>; with the ſinners, <hi>Euill ſhall not come</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Amos 9.10.</note> with the grieuous treſpaſſers, <hi>Euill ſhall not come vpon vs, the Prophets are but winde, and the word is not in them</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Ier. 5.12.13.</note>; with the frozen in their dregges, <hi>The Lord will do neither good nor euill</hi>
               <note n="t" place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note>. For as the Lord liueth (it is his owne atteſtation) if he whet his glittering ſword, and his hand take hold on iudgement, hee will render vengeance on his enemies, and reward them that hate him, hee will make his arrowes drunke with their bloud, and his ſword ſhall deuoure their fleſh <note n="u" place="margin">Deut. 32.40.41.42.</note>.</p>
            <p>But I haue many things to ſay, I paſſe from the certainty, and come to the ſubiect or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:14447:8"/>vpon whom this vengeance muſt bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted: <hi>A Tree.</hi>] Now all Trees are not of one ſort, of one ranke, for ſome are Trees of the Forreſt, ſome of the Garden: What Trees then muſt this Axe hew at? Not thoſe of the Forreſt; For what hath hee to doe to iudge them being without <note n="x" place="margin">1. Cor. 5.12.</note> but the Trees of the Garden, for them hee iudgeth being within <note n="y" place="margin">Ibidem.</note>, and in the Garden, Not thoſe flouriſhing Palmes, that bring forth fruite ſtill <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 92.12.13</note>, but thoſe <hi>ligna arida,</hi> dry Trees <note n="a" place="margin">Eſay 56.3.</note>: Such as will bee Citizens of <hi>Syon,</hi> and yet not ſuffer the Lord that reigneth in <hi>Syon</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Eſay 52.7.</note>, to rule ouer them <note n="c" place="margin">Luk. 19.14.27</note>; Such as will bee in the Vineyard, yet will yeeld no fruite to the Lord of the Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 21.34.</note>; for ſuch Chaffe will grow with the Wheate <note n="e" place="margin">Math. 13.</note>, ſuch Tares will ſpring vp with the good Seed, and ſuch veſſels of diſhonour will thruſt themſelues into the great houſe of Gods Militant Church <note n="f" place="margin">2. Tim. 2.20.</note>, though being in the Church, they are not of the Church <note n="g" place="margin">1. Iohn 2.9.</note>; no more then the Elect being in the world, are of the world <note n="h" place="margin">Ioh. 15.19.</note>. Thoſe Phariſees then of the Conciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, the brethren of the Separation, which ſtand apart, will not come neere our Churches, as though they were holier and ſounder then they <note n="i" place="margin">Eſay 56.5.</note>, and which can finde no reſt for the ſoale of their foote, but the Synagogue of <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> are not led with the feruour of zeale, but tranſpor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the fury of Schiſme, whilſt they leaue Gods Floare becauſe of ſome Chaffe, breake his net becauſe of ſome baggage of fiſh, depart
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:14447:9"/>out of his houſe becauſe of ſome veſſels of diſhonour, and forſake his field becauſe of ſome cockle: <hi>Non propter malos boni deſerendi,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Anguſt. epiſt. <hi>48.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſed propter bonos mali tolerandi:</hi> Good men are not to be forſaken for ill mens ſakes, but the ill are rather to be tolerated for the goods ſake. Doth the Oliue Tree preſently looſe his fatneſſe, or the Fig-tree his ſweetneſſe, becauſe the pricking bramble groweth neere them? Doth the Lillie ceaſe to be a Lillie, becauſe it is amongſt the Thornes <note n="l" place="margin">Cant. 2.2.</note>? Hath our Mother loſt her beauty, yea her face it ſelfe, if there bee a ſpot or ſcratch vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it? <hi>Eccleſiam teneo</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi>
               <note n="m" place="margin">Augſt. lib. <hi>3.</hi> contra Creſcon. grammat. cap. <hi>35</hi>
               </note>) <hi>&amp;c. I abide in the Church being full of Wheate and Chaffe, I amend thoſe that I can, I tolerate thoſe that I cannot amend, I flye from the Chaffe leaſt I ſhould be it, but not from the Floare, leaſt I ſhould be nothing:</hi> But they being carryed about with <hi>euery blaſt of vaine doctrine</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.14.</note>, ſtill innouating their Poſitions, ſtill new hammering their Church Conſtitutions, ſhew themſelues to bee but Chaffe. <hi>Tu qui vento tentationis euobaſti, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Auſten</hi>) <hi>Thou which art blowne out of the Floare with the winde of temptation, what art thou? Wheate: the winde would not carry it out of the floare: By the place therefore where thou art, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge what thou art.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to leaue the purſute of theſe fugitiues, &amp; to come neerer to our ſelues; if this muſt bee done to theſe drie barren trees <note n="o" place="margin">Luke 23.32.</note>, though they want not leaues to couer their nakednes, <note n="p" place="margin">Math. 21.19.</note> thogh
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:14447:9"/>they haue a name and place within the walls of Gods houſe, <note n="q" place="margin">Eſay 56.5.</note> what profiteth it them to reſt in an outward profeſſion, ſhew of godlines, &amp; to want the inward power, and life thereof? to be painted Sepulchres, beautifull without, loathſome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <note n="r" place="margin">Math. 23 27.</note>, <hi>foris Catones, intus Nerones,</hi> outwardly as graue as <hi>Cato,</hi> inwardly as wilde as <hi>Nero:</hi> and as Saint <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeaketh, <hi>in ſuperficie boni, in alto mali;</hi> in the outſide good, in the inſide euil: and to haue our fruit like to the Apple of <hi>Sodome,</hi> which <note n="ſ" place="margin">Solinus.</note> 
               <hi>in the outſide hath a ſhew of ripeneſſe, but in the inſide ſmoaky duſt, ſo that vpon the leaſt touch it ſendeth out ſmoke, and goeth away in a flying duſt.</hi> Shall the wolfe euer be ſet on the right hand, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee commeth ſometimes in ſheepes cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing? <note n="t" place="margin">Math. 7.19.</note> Shall not Sathan fall from Heauen like lightning, <note n="u" place="margin">Luke 10.18.</note> though heere hee often transforme himſelfe into an Angell of light? <note n="x" place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note> Shall not the fiue fooliſh Virgins, that brought with them the lamps of an outward profeſſion onely, and wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the oyle of grace, bee ſhut out of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome? <note n="y" place="margin">Math. 25.10.</note> Could <hi>Ahab</hi> eſcape the ſtroake of the arrow, though hee were diſguiſed in his habite? <note n="z" place="margin">1. King. 22.34.</note> And ſhall men, though they ſweare vaine, falſe oathes, commit murther, adultery and ſuch like wickedneſſe, be deliuered if they come and ſtand before God in his houſe? <note n="a" place="margin">Ier. 7.9.10.</note> Aſſuredly ſuch hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting betweene God and world, will make vs <hi>pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere inter coelum &amp; terram,</hi> hang betweene hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen and earth (as <hi>Eraſmus</hi> was painted) yea <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere coelum &amp; terram,</hi> looſe both heauen &amp; earth;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:14447:10"/>the world hating vs, becauſe wee are Chriſtians ſo much as in appearance, God hating vs dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, becauſe wee are Chriſtians but in appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance.</p>
            <p>But that none may dreame of any ſtarting cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, hope for any lurking holes here, that great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe may not keepe out of the way <hi>Cum priuile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio,</hi> that meaneneſſe may not thinke to be retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with a <hi>non eſt inuentus,</hi> let vs caſt our eyes vpon the extent, it is euery ſuch <hi>barrentrer,</hi> that this Axe muſt doe execution vpon. It is not <hi>in foro poli,</hi> in the Court of heauen, as it is <hi>in foro ſoli,</hi> in the earthly Courts; where the greater flies break through the Spider webs of the lawes, and eſcape, and the leſſer are onely caught; and where a <hi>Dauid</hi> that ſitteth on the Throne findeth ſome ſonnes of <hi>Zeruich</hi> too hard for him, ſo that he cannot reward the doer of euill according to his wickedneſſe: But this Iudge of the whole world (who iudgeth without any reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons) <note n="b" place="margin">Roman. 2.11.</note> will doe right, in giuing to euery ſuch fruitleſſe tree the recompence of their curſed barrenneſſe, in deſtroying vtterly euery enemie that doth euill in his Sanctuary, <note n="c" place="margin">Pſalm. 7.4.3</note> whether Iew or Gentile, <note n="d" place="margin">Roman. 2.9.</note> whether naturall branch or ingraf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed, <note n="e" place="margin">Rom. 11.21.</note> whether low or high, rich or poore, <note n="f" place="margin">Pſalm. 49.2.</note> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſitting vpon the Throne, or being captiue in the priſon, <note n="g" place="margin">Exod. 12.29</note> whether people or prieſt, ſeruant or maiſter, maid or miſtreſſe, buyer or ſeller, lender or borrower, taker of vſury or giuer of vſury; <note n="h" place="margin">Iſaiah. 24.21.</note> and to vſe Saint <hi>Auſtent</hi> words in another caſe, <hi>quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:14447:10"/>aliud dioi poteſt, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Auguſt. Tract. <hi>52</hi> in Iohem.</note> 
               <hi>Whatſoeuer elſe may bee ſpoken, according to thoſe innumerable differences, whereby men differ one from another, from the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to the loweſt, from the King to the begger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>ventus vrens,</hi> ſcorching winde then of the Lords indignation, ſhall not only light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or blight the lowe ſhrubbes, the thiſtle of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon,</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">2. King. 14 9.</note> the hyſſope that groweth vpon the wall, <note n="l" place="margin">1. King 4.34.</note> but alſo the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> that are high, <note n="m" place="margin">2. King. 19 23</note> for their eminency, excellent <note n="n" place="margin">Cant. 5 12.</note> for their glorie, the Cedars of God <note n="o" place="margin">Pſalm. 80.10.</note> for their dignity. The voice of the Lord, the thunderbolt of his wrath, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the Cedars, yea breaketh the Cedars of <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon</hi> in peeces, <note n="p" place="margin">Pſalm. 29.5.</note> he will prepare deſtroyers for theſe chiefe Cedars, and caſt them into the fire. <note n="q" place="margin">Ierem. 22.7.</note> 
               <hi>Zedekiah</hi> an high Cedar muſt be taken in Gods nette, and brought to <hi>Babylon,</hi> there to receiue his iudgement. <note n="r" place="margin">Eze. 17.20.22</note> Yea the higher they ſtand, the more frequent, the more vehement is the blow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the beating of the winde of Gods indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on againſt them, according to that of the <note n="ſ" place="margin">Horat. Carmin lib. <hi>2.</hi> Ode <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> Poet.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>Sapius ventis agitatur ingens</l>
               <l>Pinus, &amp; celſae grauiore caſu</l>
               <l>Decidunt turres, feriunt<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſummos fulgur a montes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>With windes is often toſs'd the Pine tree tall,</l>
               <l>And higheſt towers with greateſt ruine fall,</l>
               <l>And tops of mountains lightnings of tenſt ſmite.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Horribly and ſpeedily, will God appeare to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that be in high places, a ſore triall ſhall be to the mightie <note n="t" place="margin">Wiſd 6.5.8.</note>, he ſhall cut off the ſpirit of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:14447:11"/>and is terrible to the kings of the earth <note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 76.12.</note>. For are not they vnder God? as <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſpeaketh of himſelfe <note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 50.19.</note>, and being ſo vnder God, that they are <hi>ſolo Deo minores</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Tertul. ad Scapulam. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> onely leſſer then God, they doe <hi>ſoli deo peccare,</hi> ſinne onely againſt God, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid of himſelfe <note n="z" place="margin">Pſal. 51.4.</note>, and muſt giue accounts of their doings at Gods tribunal ſeat only Gods anointing being vpon them, thought they ſhould hunt after our liues, as after a Partridge in the mountaines <note n="a" place="margin">1. Sam. 29.20</note>, yet muſt we not cut off the lappes of their garments <note n="b" place="margin">1. Sam. 24.6.</note>. Neither on the other ſide, is this day of the Lord of Hoſts onely vpon all that is exalted, vpon the Cedars of <hi>Lebanon</hi> that are high and exalted, and vpon all the Ol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhan,</hi> and vpon all the high mountaines, and vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all the hilles that are lifted vp, and vpon eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry high to wel, and vpon euery ſtrong wall, <hi>ſuper valentiſsimos &amp; mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tiſsimo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> vpon thoſe that are moſt ſtrong and fenced; as <hi>Iunius</hi> gloſſeth the words, and vpon all the ſhips of <hi>Tarſhiſh,</hi> and all pleaſant pictures; <hi>ſuper opulentiſsimos &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rnatiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos,</hi> vpon them that are moſt wealthy and gay <note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 12.16. <hi>&amp; Iunius Ibid.</hi>
               </note>: but alſo vpon the Firre trees, that is, <hi>populares quoſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan>,</hi> all the people, and the forreſt of the vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage, that is, <hi>promiſcuum numerum tenuium è po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulo, the confuſed number of the poore amongſt the people</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Zach. 11.2. <hi>&amp; Iunius Ibid.</hi>
               </note>. <hi>Howle Firre tree for the Cedar is fallen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe all the mightie are ſpoyled. Howle ô yee Okes of Baſhan, for the forreſt of the vintage is come downe.</hi> The meane man muſt be brought downe as well as the mightie humbled <note n="e" place="margin">Eſay 5.25</note>, for euery man muſt
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:14447:11"/>beare his owne burthen <note n="f" place="margin">Galat. 6.5.</note>, euery one giue an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of himſelfe to God <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 14.12.</note>, and euery man re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue the things that he hath done, according to that which he hath done <note n="h" place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10.</note>.</p>
            <p>But what is the cauſe why ſo certainly, ſo ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally, euery ſuch tree muſt be ſo dealt withall? For Gods thoughts are not as mans thoughts, his wayes as mans wayes <note n="i" place="margin">Eſay 55.9.</note>, that he ſhould bate a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vn worthily, condemne them vndeſeruedly. No man can complaine of him, as <hi>Dauid</hi> the type, and Chriſt the Antitype of their haters, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>They hated mee without a cauſe</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 35 19. Iohn 15.25.</note>. It is a mans voyce, or rather a deuils, not Gods; <hi>Non amote Sabidi, nec poſſum dicere quare;</hi> I loue thee not. <hi>Sabidius,</hi> but I cannot tell why. As <hi>Dauid</hi> then anſwered his brother when hee chec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked him, for comming to the warre, <hi>Is there not a cauſe</hi>
               <note n="l" place="margin">1. Sam. 17.29.</note>? So is there not a cauſe of the Lords warre againſt theſe Trees? Surely euery Tree at his firſt creation, had his bleſſing to bring forth fruite according to his kinde <note n="m" place="margin">Gen. 1.11.</note>; and theſe Trees of the Garden if they will bee created a new in Chriſt Ieſus <note n="n" place="margin">Ephe. 2.10.</note>, muſt haue a bleſſing to bring forth fruite in him; which, if with pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Eſau</hi>
               <note n="o" place="margin">Heb. 12.16.</note>, they haue ſet light by <note n="p" place="margin">Gen. 25.33.34.</note>, they are fit for nothing but the Axe, and good for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but the fire: Being then with the curſed Fig-tree barren <note n="q" place="margin">Math. 21.19.</note>, <hi>not bringing forth good fruite</hi>] the Lord who is righteous in all his waies, holy in all his workes <note n="r" place="margin">Pſal. 145.17.</note>, cannot bee vnrighteous in executing this vengeance vpon them.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:14447:12"/>
Wee ſee then the euidence that is heere giuen in againſt them, They <hi>bring not forth good fruit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now that wee may not thinke them thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned before their cauſe (though it bee not vnheard) be well vnderſtood, that wee may not cry with the Eunuch heere, <hi>How can we vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand without a guide</hi>
               <note n="ſ" place="margin">Actes 8.31.</note>, <hi>Nouerint vniuerſi,</hi> bee it knowne to all, that the fruites wherein they faile, are the fruits of righteouſneſſe, wherewith they ſhould bee filled <note n="t" place="margin">Phil. 1.11.</note>, good workes, wherein they ſhould bee fruitfull <note n="u" place="margin">Col. 1.10.</note>, the fruites of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, in all goodneſſe, righteouſneſſe, and truth <note n="x" place="margin">Ephe. 6.9.</note>. Now theſe fruits are not all of one ſort, are not all ſubiect to one conſideration; for ſome of them are generall, growing vpon all the Trees of the Garden, vpon all the branches that are graffed in the true Vine, ſuch as are thoſe good fruits of the Spirit to bee found on euery good Tree, <hi>Loue, Ioy, Peace, Long-ſuffering, Gentleneſſe, Goodneſſe, Faith, Meekneſſe, Tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">Gal. 5.22i</note>; Some are ſpeciall, particular, which euery Tree muſt bring forth according to his kind, as being his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> proper fruite, whereby hee muſt bee knowne <note n="z" place="margin">Luke 6.42.</note> in that Calling wherein God hath ſet him. For thus the Oliue Tree hath his fatneſſe, the Fig Tree his ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <note n="a" place="margin">Iudges 9 13</note>, the Vine his <hi>Vinum laetificans,</hi> Wine <hi>that cheareth God and Man,</hi> and euery Tree plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the riuers of the waters of the Sanctuary, bringeth forth <hi>fructum ſuum,</hi> his owne <hi>fruite in due ſeaſon</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note>. As then (according to that diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:14447:12"/>made by Saint <hi>Auſten</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Auſt. Epiſt. <hi>50</hi>
               </note>) a King ſerueth God after one ſort, as hee is a man, after another ſort, as hee is a King: As hee is a man, hee ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth him by liuing faithfully; as hee is a King al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, hee ſerueth him by ordaining Lawes that command Iuſtice, and forbid the contrary with conuenient authority. So all the houſhold of faith oweth a ſeruice to God, after one ſort in the generall fruites of holineſſe <note n="d" place="margin">Rom. 6.21.</note>, and after another ſort in the proper fruites of a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Calling, and as they are the ſeuerall Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of one Myſticall Body; if Heads, in Ruling; if Eyes, in looking about; if Hands, in wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king; if Feete, in walking. For thus beſides thoſe generall duties of piety, which lie equally on euery ones ſhoulders, the Princes fruite, that ſitteth on the Throne, is to doe equity and rightouſneſſe <note n="e" place="margin">1. King. 10 9.</note>, to bee (as <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zers</hi> Tree ſhewed to him in a viſion) faire and fruitfull, hauing meate in it for all, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſhadow for all the beaſts of the field, and and ſpreading its boughes that the fowles of the aire may dwell in it, and of which all fleſh may be ſed <note n="f" place="margin">Daniel 4.9.</note> the honorable mans fruite, to hold it his greateſt honour with <hi>Iabeſh,</hi> to call vpon the name of the Lord <note n="g" place="margin">1. Chron. 9.10.</note>, to honor him by whom he is honored, to open his treaſures, and to offer gifts vnto Chriſt <note n="h" place="margin">Math. 2.11.</note>. The Iudges fruit to execute iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment truly and vprightly in the gate <note n="i" place="margin">Zach. 8.16.</note>, the man of warres fruite, to do violence to no man, to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe no man falſely, and to bee content with his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:14447:13"/>wages <note n="k" place="margin">Luk. 3.14.18.</note>. The Paſtors fruite, to rule well in the houſe of <hi>God,</hi> to labour in the word &amp; doctrine <note n="l" place="margin">1. Tim. 5.17.</note>. The rich mans fruit, to bee rich in diſtributing and communicating <note n="m" place="margin">1. Tim. 6.18.</note>. The ſubiects fruit, to yeeld obedience to Principalities and Powers <note n="n" place="margin">Titus 3.1.</note>. The ſeruants fruit, to be ſubiect to their Maſters, and pleaſe them in all things <note n="o" place="margin">Titus 2.9.</note>. And in a word, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery particular mans fruit wherein hee is called, therein to walke and abide before God <note n="p" place="margin">1. Cor. 7.20.</note>. And as the figge tree cannot bring forth Oliues, nor the vine figges <note n="q" place="margin">Iam 3.12.</note>: ſo neither ought one of theſe trees planted in the courts of the Lords houſe, bring forth the fruit that is peculiar to another, but ſtill euery one according to his kinde. <hi>Simcon</hi> and <hi>Leui</hi> brought not forth <hi>fructum ſuum,</hi> their fruit, when they ſlew <hi>Hamor</hi> &amp; <hi>Sechem</hi> that had abuſed their ſiſter as a whore <note n="r" place="margin">Gen. 34.26.</note> For vengeance is Gods <note n="ſ" place="margin">Deut. 32.35.</note>, &amp; this power to execute vengeance he hath de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legated to the Gods of the earth, tying priuate mens hands therefrom. <hi>Corah, Duthan,</hi> and <hi>Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram</hi> with their company, brought not forth their fruit, when being not of the ſeed of <hi>Aaron,</hi> they would come neere to offer incenſe before the Lord <note n="t" place="margin">Num. 16.40.</note> 
               <hi>Vzzah</hi> not his fruit when he put his hand to the Arke of God, and held it <note n="u" place="margin">2. Sam. 6.6.</note>, which was the <hi>Leuites</hi> charge, and neere to which no ſtranger might come <note n="x" place="margin">Num. 18.4.</note>. <hi>Vzziah</hi> the King not his fruit when he went into the Temple to burne incenſe vpon the Altar of incenſe, which pertained to the Prieſts that were conſecrated to offer incenſe <note n="y" place="margin">2. Chr. 26.17 18.</note>. The baſe bramble not his fruit, when he would be
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14447:13"/>annointed King ouer the trees. <note n="z" place="margin">Iudges 9.15.</note> For he by whom Kings doe reigne <note n="a" place="margin">Frou. 8.15.</note> neuer ſet ſuch trees on the Throne. Seruants, not their fruite, when they ride on horſe-backe, and cauſe Princes to walke as ſeruants on the ground <note n="b" place="margin">Eccleſ. 10.6.</note>. The vagabond Iewes, not their fruite, when they tooke in hand to adiure the euill ſpirits by Ieſus whom <hi>Paul</hi> Preached <note n="c" place="margin">Actes 9.13.</note>, for that Ieſus who onely could com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand the vncleane ſpirits, had neuer ſaid vnto them, caſt out deuils <note n="d" place="margin">Math. 10.8.</note> Priute ſpirits, not their fruite, when they would reforme Temples, throw out Idoles, and put downe either reall or ſuppoſed abhominations: For their fruite is, to keepe themſelues from Idoles <note n="e" place="margin">1. Ioh. 5.21.</note>, not to lay hands on Idoles; to beware of bowing to <hi>Baal</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">1. King. 19.18.</note>, not to meddle with breaking of <hi>Baal</hi> in peeces; to refuſe to fall downe before a <hi>Nebuchadnez<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zars</hi> Images <note n="g" place="margin">Dan. 3.6.</note>, but not to throw it downe. Our reformed Siſters, not their fruite, when they climbe into <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire, and will bee Doctors of the Law; For Saint <hi>Paul</hi> hath long ſince inhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited, ſuſpended ſuch exceſſe of zeale: <hi>I permit not a woman to teach, nor to vſurpe authority ouer the man, but to be in ſilence.</hi>
               <note n="h" place="margin">1. Tim. 2.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>But to leaue this enumeration of particulars, <hi>In quibus non tam copia quam modus quaerendus eſt,</hi> wherein I muſt not ſo much ſeeke for ſtore as keep meaſure. From this euidence here brought in againſt theſe Trees, that they want <hi>good fruit,</hi> ariſeth another caſe in Diuinity, whereby wee may bee reſolued, that it is not enough to bee
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:14447:14"/>harmeleſſe in forbearing of euill, but wee muſt alſo be fruitfull in doing of good: And that our righteouſneſſe muſt not onely bee priuatiue, in <hi>ceaſing to do euill</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">Eſay. 1.16.</note>, but alſo poſitiue, in <hi>learning to do well: Abhorre that which is euill, cleaue to that which is good</hi>
               <note n="k" place="margin">Rom. 12.9.</note>. The curſe cleaueth vnto the Fig-tree, not becauſe it had Figges (ſuch as <hi>Ieremy</hi> ſaw) very naughty, which could not bee eaten, they were ſo euill <note n="l" place="margin">Ier. 24.2.</note>, but for want of good Figges <note n="m" place="margin">Mar. 21.19.</note>. And <hi>Iobs</hi> letters of commendation that hee carryeth, as it were, from God to men, runne in this tenour, that hee was not onely harmeleſſe in eſchewing euill, but alſo vpright in working of good <note n="n" place="margin">Iob. 1.1.</note>. And all the Sheepe in Chriſts Fold muſt not onely bee innocent in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing none euill, but alſo fruitfull in bringing forth thouſands and ten thouſands in the Courts of his Gares. They that haue learned Chriſt, are taught by his ſauing grace, not onely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny vngodlineſſe and worldly luſts, but alſo to liue ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent world <note n="o" place="margin">Titus 2.11.</note>: Not onely to caſt away the workes of darkneſſe, but alſo to put on them the armour of light <note n="p" place="margin">Rom. 13.12.</note>. Yea euen that Phariſie, whoſe praiſe was of men, not of God; whoſe outſide onely had a faire ſhew, his inſide being full of filthines, and whoſe iuſtifying himſelfe before men, made him abhominable in the ſight of God; <note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 16.15.</note> ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth the Trumpet of his owne praiſe, not onely for omiſſion of euill, <hi>God I thanke thee, that I am not as other men are, extortioners, vniuſt, adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrers,</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:14447:14"/>but alſo for the operation of good, <hi>I faſt twiſe in the weeke, I giue tithes of all that I poſſeſſe</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Luk. 18.11.12</note>, whoſe righteouſneſſe, if wee exceed not in righteouſneſſe, wee cannot enter into the Kingdome of God <note n="ſ" place="margin">Math. 5.20.</note>. Let the oppreſſour then, not onely, not with-hold the pledge, nor ſpoyle by violence; but alſo giue his bread to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry, and couer the naked with a garment; <note n="t" place="margin">Ezek. 18.16.</note>; yea, with <hi>Zacheus,</hi> reſtore foure-fold to him that hee hath wronged, either by feigned cauillation, or by horrible extortion <note n="u" place="margin">Luke 19.8.</note>: and of the reſt giue Almes, yea ſanctifie an halfe, <hi>In pios vſus,</hi> to good vſes, that the whole may bee cleane vnto him <note n="x" place="margin">Luke 11.41.</note>. Let the ſwearer not onely vtter no blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy, but alſo bleſſe God with that tongue wherewith he hath blaſphemed him: The adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terer not onely abſtaine from fornication, but alſo poſſeſſe his veſſell in holineſſe and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour <note n="y" place="margin">1. Theſſ. 4.3.4</note>. The Vſurer, not onely looſe the bands of wickedneſſe, and take off the heauy burthens <note n="z" place="margin">Eſay 58.6.7.</note>; but alſo breake his bread to the hungry, bring the poore, that are caſt out, to his houſe, and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the naked, when he ſeeth him. The lyer, not onely caſt off lying, but alſo ſpeake the truth vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his neighbour <note n="a" place="margin">Epeſ. 4.25.</note> The Thiefe, not onely not ſteale any more, but alſo labour, working with his hands the thing that is good, that hee may haue to giue to him that needeth <note n="b" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.28.</note>. And in a word, let the wicked not onely forſake his wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked waies <note n="c" place="margin">Eſay 55.7.</note>, but alſo turne into the waies of righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe. Otherwiſe, if (like to that conceit
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:14447:15"/>which Atheiſts haue of God) we will neither do good nor euill <note n="d" place="margin">Zeph. 1.12.</note>, our doome ſhall not bee ſo eaſie as to be throwne into that feyned <hi>Limbus,</hi> either of the Fathers that dyed before Chriſt, or of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants that die vnbaptized, where we ſhall neither enioy good nor euill <note n="e" place="margin">Bel. lib. <hi>2.</hi> de purgator. cap. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note>: But as in the omitting of good it is impoſſible not to commit euill, ſo for our both omiſſion of good, and commiſſion of euill, wee ſhall be ſhut out of heauen, where is all good, and throwne into hell where is all euill.</p>
            <p>Againe, if theſe Trees that bring not forth good fruite bee heere threatned with the fire, what ſhall become of thoſe Trees, whoſe fruite like the Vines of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> is as bitter as gall <note n="f" place="margin">Deut. 32.32.</note>; yea vpon euery branch of which, there groweth nothing but rotten, ſtinking, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſauory fruite, and whereof all the members are ſeruants to vncleanneſſe and to iniquity, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit iniquity <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 6.19.</note>; whoſe hearts within them ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine miſchiefe <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 58.2.</note>, whoſe hands without them ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute cruelty vpon the earth, and whoſe right hands are full of bribes <note n="i" place="margin">Pſal. 26.10.</note>, whoſe feete run to euill and make haſt to ſhed bloud <note n="k" place="margin">Pro. 1.10.</note>; whoſe cares are vncircumſciſed <note n="l" place="margin">Act. 7.51.</note>; whoſe eyes are full of all adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, and cannot ceaſe to ſin <note n="m" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.14.</note>; <hi>Whoſe throates are open ſepulchres, whoſe tongues are vſed to deceit, vnder whoſe lips is the poyſon of Aſpes, whoſe mouthes are full of curſing and bitterneſſe</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Rom. 3.13.14</note>? Yea out of whoſe noſthriles (ſo full hath Sathan filled euery member with iniquity) commeth out
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:14447:15"/>ſmoake, as out of a boyling pot or caldron, like to that <hi>Leuiathan</hi>
               <note n="p" place="margin">Iob 41.11.</note>, and all whoſe daies are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed not onely like ſmoake <note n="q" place="margin">Pſal. 102.3.</note>, but euen in ſmoake and fumes. And if the rich Glutton lie in the torments of hell, whoſe pride of apparell was but in purple and fine linnen <note n="r" place="margin">Luk. 16.19.</note>, what riuers of burning brimſtone ſhall bee kindled againſt them, who with <hi>Lucullus</hi> haue <hi>ducent as veſtes pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pureas</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Plutarch. in vita Luculli.</note>, <hi>two hundred purple garments,</hi> and with <hi>Nero</hi> haue new euery day, and throw away the old <note n="t" place="margin">Sueton. in vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta Neronis.</note>: and with the Princes children are cloa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſtrange apparrell <note n="u" place="margin">Zeph. 1.8.</note>, being ſo variable in their faſhions, that as it is growne to a by-word of <hi>Poland,</hi> by reaſon of the toleration of men of euery ſect and religion there, that if any one haue loſt his religion, he may find it there or no where: ſo it may of them, that if any nation haue loſt their faſhion, they may find it amongſt them or not at all <note n="x" place="margin">Sir <hi>Edwin Sands</hi> his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligions.</note>? If he who fared only <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (as ſaith the originall) <hi>neatly and delicatly euery day,</hi> what they who riſe vp early to follow gluttony and drunkenneſſe, and continue till night, till they be inflamed <note n="y" place="margin">Eſay 5.11.</note>, yea till all their Tables be full of filthy vomitting <note n="z" place="margin">Eſay 28.8.</note>. If hee who clothed his backe, and filled his belly with his owne: what they whoſe backes are clothed with the ſpoyles of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and their bellies filled with the bread of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit and rapine? If he who would not vouchſafe his crummes to hungry <hi>Lazarus,</hi> what they who eate vp the poore as bread <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 14.4.</note>? <hi>Hinc magnopere colli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gendum, &amp;c.</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi> on theſe words) <hi>we
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:14447:16"/>may hence ſufficiently gather, with what puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he ſhall be puniſhed which taketh away another mans goods, if he be caſt into the damnation of hell, which giueth not his owne.</hi> And <hi>ſi in ignem mitti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur</hi> (as S. <hi>Auſten</hi> ſpeaketh in the caſe of the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <note n="b" place="margin">Aug. de verbis Domini ſerm. <hi>20</hi>
               </note>, &amp;c. <hi>If he muſt be caſt into the fire that hath preyed vpon another mans? If hee burne not giuen his owne goods, whither ſhall hee bee ſent that hath preyed vpon another mans? If hee burne with the Diuell that hath not clothed the naked, where thinkeſt thou ſhall hee burne that hath ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led him?</hi> And if they muſt goe captiue with the firſt, that are not ſorry for the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Amos 6.6.7.</note>, ſhall not they be bound hand and foot, and caſt into vtter darkneſſe <note n="d" place="margin">Mat. 22.13.</note>, that haue cauſed the affliction of <hi>Ioſeph?</hi> If folly bee layd to his charge that went but about to lay vp the fruits of his owne grounds <note n="e" place="margin">Luk. 12.20.</note>, ſhall not bitter things bee written againſt them that enter into the fields of the Fatherleſſe, and deuoure the houſes of Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes? <hi>Si ſtultus eſt qui recondit ſua</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Aug. de verbis Domini ſerm. <hi>19</hi>
               </note>, <hi>vos inuenite nomen eius, qui rapit aliena.</hi> If he be a foole which hoordeth vp his owne, finde yee out a name for him that taketh away another mans.</p>
            <div type="application">
               <head>An application of the Text to the preſent ſolemnity of the fift day of Auguſt.</head>
               <p>BVt all this while I may ſay vnto my ſelfe, as the Lepers that met with the ſpoyles of the the Hoſt of the Syrians, one to another <note n="g" place="margin">2. King. 7.9.</note>, I do
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:14447:16"/>not well. This is a day of good tidings, and ſhal I hold my peace? This is a day which the Lord hath made (as truly may it be ſaid of our preſent Soueraignes preſeruation, as of <hi>Dauids</hi> either coronation or exaltation) &amp; ſhal we not reioyce and be glad therein <note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 118.24.</note>? Shall I not intreat in my ſpeech of the King, and of his great deliuerance? Let the leproſie of theſe cleaue as inſeparably vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me, as euer the leproſie of <hi>Naaman</hi> did cleaue vnto <hi>Gehezi</hi>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">2. King. 5.27.</note>, if it bee not as ioyfull a thing vnto me to ſpeake of the honour of this day, as it was to thoſe foure Lepers to publiſh in Samaria the the happy tidings of the Syrians flight Oh that my tongue were as the pen of a ready writer <note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note>, that my voyce were lifted vp as a trumpet <note n="l" place="margin">Iſai 58.1.</note>, to found out vnto you the great works of our God, and the mercies that he hath ſhewed vnto his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed. And that the words of my mouth may be as words ſpoken in due ſeaſon, the matter that I will vtter ſhall be built vpon the foundation of this preſent Text. For I may be bold to ſay vnto you, that euen this day hath this Scripture beene fulfilled in our eares, which haue heard of, and in our eyes, which haue ſeene, certaine trees that budded forth (for that they brought it not to maturitie, it was the Lords doing) corrupt, rot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, abhominable fruit <hi>(quis poteſt verbis aequare dolorem?)</hi> cut downe with the Axe of diuine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, and throwne into the fire, euen into the fire of hell. What theſe trees were, what their fruit, &amp; how hewne downe, <hi>audite &amp; obſtupeſcite,</hi>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:14447:17"/>behold, and in beholding wonder with great maruell. Theſe Trees then (which, as time the mother of truth, hath manifeſted, had many ſpreading branches <note n="m" place="margin">
                     <hi>Reſtalrigge</hi> with his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant <hi>Boux.</hi> and <hi>Sprotte</hi> their acceſſary, with other aid, mentioned in <hi>Reſtalrigges</hi> let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the Farle of <hi>Gow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.</hi> See <hi>Sprottes arraignment.</hi>
                  </note>) were not the Thiſtles of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> exalting themſelues againſt the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar <note n="n" place="margin">2. King. 14 9.</note>; nor yet the Brambles of the wood, deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to be annointed Kings <note n="o" place="margin">Iudges 9.15.</note>, (although Thiſtles and Brambles, for their pricking and piercing) for then it had beene eaſie to haue troden downe ſuch Thiſtles, a fire would quickly haue come out of the Cedar, and haue conſumed ſuch Brambles: But they were a couple of the Oakes of <hi>Baſhan,</hi> (ſo the Prophet calleth the mighty men of the Land <note n="p" place="margin">Eſay 2.13.</note>) a paire of brethren; a <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Leui,</hi> brethren in euill <note n="q" place="margin">Gen. 49.5.</note>; <hi>Ioah</hi> and <hi>Abiſhai</hi> ſonnes of <hi>Zeruiah,</hi> that thought to haue beene too hard for our <hi>Dauid</hi>
                  <note n="r" place="margin">2. Sam. 3.39.</note>: Neither were they Trees of the Forreſt, open enemies, againſt whom there might haue beene, either defence, or hiding <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 55.12.</note> ſtrangers for Nation or Religion, as <hi>Egyptians</hi> to <hi>Hebrewes,</hi> who held it abhominati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to eate bread one with another <note n="t" place="margin">Gen. 43.32.</note>; as <hi>Iewes</hi> to <hi>Samaritans,</hi> who meddle not one with another <note n="u" place="margin">Iohn 4.9.</note>, (which yet ſhould not haue touched Gods An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noynted <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 105.12.13.14.</note>; for was not the <hi>Amalekites</hi> bloud vpon him for touching of <hi>Saul</hi> the Lords Annointed, though he were a ſtranger and no Subiect <note n="y" place="margin">2. Sam. 1.16.</note>) But euen Trees of the Garden, men of the ſame lip and ſpeech, that were in ſubiection vnder this Cedar, owing him a ſeruice in the Lord, with their goods, body, yea the ſacrifice of their dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:14447:17"/>bloud, men worſhipping the ſame God with him after the ſame manner, to whom there was one Lord, one faith, one Baptiſme with him <note n="z" place="margin">Epheſ. 4.5.</note>, who profeſſed as <hi>Ruth</hi> to <hi>Naomi, thy God ſhall bee my God</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">Ruth. 1.16.</note>; and who went together into the houſe of the ſame God, as companions in the ſame Religion <note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 55.14.</note>; yea Trees ſo clad in the leaues of an outward ſeeming zeale, that euen this very day, the elder of them kept an <hi>Ahabs</hi> faſt, when <hi>Naboth</hi> muſt die <note n="c" place="margin">1. King. 21.12.</note> and with <hi>Abſolom</hi> pretended a vow, when he would rebell <note n="d" place="margin">2. Sam. 15.8.</note>, came and ſtood before God in his Houſe <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Alexander</hi> would haue his Maieſty arriue there, whilſt the Earle his brother was at Sermon. See <hi>Gowries</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy.</note>, vouchſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fing an care to the Goſpell of peace, which hath brought and taught all peace, when warre and bloud was in his heart; when hee purpoſed to haue mingled his ſacrifice with the bloud of his Soueraigne, as <hi>Pilate</hi> did the <hi>Galileans</hi> bloud with their ſacrifices <note n="e" place="margin">Luke 13.1.</note>: ſo dangerous, ſo perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious is the deuill, when hee is cloathed in white, when he commeth in the ſhape of an Angell of light <note n="f" place="margin">2. Cor. 11.14.</note>. Theſe were the Trees, Now for the ill friute that onely bloſſomed, budded forth out of them (for the moſt High blaſted it that it could not come to maturity, as that of <hi>Rechab</hi> and <hi>Baana,</hi> who ſmote King <hi>Iſhboſheth</hi> on his bed and ſlew him <note n="g" place="margin">2. Sam. 4.7.</note>, it was the fruit of ſediti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, of rebellion, which is as the ſinne of witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft <note n="h" place="margin">1. Sam. 13.52</note>, of lifting vp their hands with <hi>Abſolom</hi> againſt the Father of their Country; yea of lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violent bloud-thirſty hands vpon him, who was to them and is to vs, the light of our Iſrael <note n="i" place="margin">2. Sam. 21.17.</note>,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:14447:18"/>and the breath of our Noſthrils <note n="k" place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note>, whom they ſhould haue feared to haue laid hands on <note n="l" place="margin">2. Sam. 1.14.</note>, as being their Maiſter the Lords annointed <note n="m" place="margin">1. Sam. 24.7. &amp; 26.9.</note>, yea as being a righteous perſon (as <hi>Dauid</hi> aggraua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the ſinne of <hi>Rechab</hi> and <hi>Baana,</hi> for ſlaying a righteous perſon <note n="n" place="margin">2. Sam. 4.11</note>) one <hi>cuius virtutes nullo viti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orum confinio laeduntur,</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> faid of <hi>Traian,</hi> whoſe vertues are impaired with no neighbour vices, who neuer was an <hi>Ahab,</hi> to ſpoyle any <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>both</hi> of his Vineyard <note n="o" place="margin">1. King. 21.16.</note>, nor a <hi>Manaſſes,</hi> to defile the ſtreets of his Cities with innocent bloud <note n="p" place="margin">2. King. 21.16</note>, (ſo farre is hee from that, that hee hath pardo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned many railing <hi>Shemeis,</hi> bloudy <hi>Ioabs,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellions <hi>Abſoloms,</hi> and would euen with good <hi>Theodoſius, etiam mortuos in vitam reuocare,</hi> wiſh them aliue that are dead) nor an <hi>Herod,</hi> to take away anothers wife <note n="q" place="margin">Math. 14.4.</note>: One, to whom the Church of God doth euen owe it ſelfe, not onely for being nurſed vp with the milke of his Breaſts, but alſo for the ſeruice that hee hath done to <hi>Sion</hi> in publiſhing Apologies in her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and ſhewing himſelfe to be a defender of the faith, not onely in a Complementall Title, but alſo in actuall performance. One, whom the Common-wealth hath found as a <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzars</hi> Tree <note n="r" place="margin">Dan. 4.9.</note>, a King raigning in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and being an hiding place from the winde, a couer from the tempeſt, as Riuers of water in a dry place, as the ſhadow of a great Rocke in a weary land <note n="ſ" place="margin">Eſay 32.2.</note>: And one, of whom all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects do for his walking in and out before them,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:14447:18"/>
                  <hi>Eadem ſecretò quae palam loqui</hi>
                  <note n="t" place="margin">Seneca.</note>, ſpeake none otherwiſe in ſecret, then openly. This was their naughty deteſtable fruite; Now for the crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of it in the bud, for the hewing downe of ſuch corrupt Trees, well ſpake euen wicked <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabell; Had Zimri peace when hee ſlew his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi>
                  <note n="u" place="margin">2. King. 9.31</note>: Had theſe men peace, when they ſought, attempted to haue ſlaine their Maiſter the Lords Anointed, and had ſo farre gone on in their wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe, that they had brought him as a bird into the ſnare of the Fowler; and had dealt with their Soueraigne, as the euill ſeruant with his fellow, laid hands on him, and taken him by the throate <note n="x" place="margin">Math. 18.28.</note>? No, but euen when there was but a ſtep betweene his ſoule and death, the Lord ſtirred vp the ſpirit of ſome of thoſe mighty men, whom this our <hi>Dauid</hi> had <note n="y" place="margin">Sir <hi>Iohn Ram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſey,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Erſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ins,</hi> Sir <hi>Hugh Heries,</hi> and one <hi>Wilſon</hi> a ſeruant.</note>, whoſe hands claue vnto the ſword, and vnto whom the Lord gaue great victories that day <note n="z" place="margin">2. Sam. 23.9.10.</note>, ſo that they did beate them as ſmall as the duſt, and tread them flat as the clay of the ſtreet <note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 18.42.</note>.</p>
               <p>And as they thought to haue done not onely to their brother, but alſo to their maiſter, ſo were they retaliated, ſo was it done to them, life for life, bloud for bloud <note n="b" place="margin">Deut. 19.21.</note>, (bleſſed are they for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warding them as they would haue ſerued the Lords annoynted) although in this caſe there was great diſproportion, they ſeeking his life who was worth ten thouſand of the vulgar <note n="c" place="margin">2. Sam. 18.3.</note>: yea &amp; they found there was no inchantment againſt <hi>Iacob,</hi> no diuination againſt <hi>Iſrael</hi>
                  <note n="d" place="margin">Num. 23.23.</note>, <hi>Gowries</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chanted
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:14447:19"/>characters, wherein he did truſt, could not keepe his body from the ſword, nor his life from deſtruction <note n="e" place="margin">
                     <hi>See</hi> Gowries corſpiracie.</note>. And for their caſting into fire, euen into the fire that neuer goeth out <note n="f" place="margin">Mark. 9.43.</note>, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though we muſt be ſparing in iudging any who haue a maiſter of their owne to ſtand or fall to <note n="g" place="margin">Rom. 14.4.</note>, although <hi>Maior ſit dei benignitas</hi> (as ſaith S. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi>) <hi>quam omnium hominum iniquitas,</hi> the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God be greater then the wickedneſſe of all the men in the world, ſo that a man may bee receiued to mercy <hi>inter pontem &amp; fontem,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the bridge and the brooke: Yet if rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion threw <hi>Adam</hi> out of Paradiſe, caſt the Angels downe out of heauen into hell <note n="h" place="margin">2. Pet. 2.4.</note>, how ſhall theſe rebels, theſe traitors euer eſcape the condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hell, and be ſaued in the day of the Lord? Nay, if <hi>Iudas,</hi> in whom there was a kinde of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe, (for the Holy Ghoſt ſaith of him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <note n="i" place="margin">Mat. 27.3.</note> 
                  <hi>He Was ſorry that euer he had done the deed</hi>) and who tooke the deepeſt revenge of himſelfe that could be, (for he went and hanged himſelfe) be yet gone into his owne place <note n="k" place="margin">Acts 1.25.</note>, euen hell prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of old for him, whither are they gone, who with <hi>Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram</hi> died in their treſpaſſe <note n="l" place="margin">Num. 16.33.</note>, were neuer pricked in heart, but ſtood in defence of the deed, died in defence of it, and breathed out their laſt breath with ſorrow that they had not the wit <note n="m" place="margin">Alas I had not the <hi>weight</hi> of it, ſaid <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander.</hi> See <hi>Gowries conſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racie.</hi>
                  </note>, to haue imbrued their hands in Maieſties ſacred bloud, but euen <hi>in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernum inferius</hi> into the nethermoſt hell? And ſo euer let his enemies periſh, let the enemies of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:14447:19"/>our Lord the King, and all that riſe to doe him harme, be as thoſe two brethren, but vpon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe let his crowne flouriſh, and let the Lord ſpeak of his houſe for a great while <note n="n" place="margin">2. Sam. 7.19.</note>, that there may neuer want a man of his poſterity to ſit vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the throne of great Britaine ſo long as the Sunne and Moone endureth. And for our ſelues let vs praiſe the name of our God with a ſong, &amp; magnifie him with thankeſgiuing <note n="o" place="margin">Pſalm. 69.30</note>, who giueth ſo great deliuerance vnto his King, and ſheweth mercie vnto his annointed, and to his ſeed for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uermore <note n="p" place="margin">Pſalm. 18.50</note>. Yea let vs cry with <hi>Ahimaaz,</hi> bleſſed be the Lord which hath ſhut vp the men that lift vp their hands againſt my Lord the King <note n="q" place="margin">2. Sam. 18.28.</note> bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and thrice bleſſed be the name of the Lord, that reſerued him in <hi>meliora tempera,</hi> for better times, that he might ſet him on the throne of our Iſrael, and make him king to doe equitie and righteouſneſſe <note n="r" place="margin">2. King. 10.9.</note>. And let the King himſelfe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce in the Lords ſtrength, euen reioyce great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in his ſaluation <note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſalm. 21.1.</note>, and praiſe his God which gaue him not as a prey vnto their teeeh, but euen then when there was but a ſtep between his ſoule and death, ſent from heauen, and ſaued him from thereproach of them that would haue ſwallowed him vp <note n="t" place="margin">Pſam. 57.3.</note>, redeemed his life from the very brinkes of the graue, and crowned him with mercie and compaſſion <note n="u" place="margin">Pſalm. 103.4.</note>. So that God which hitherto hath ſaued him from the Lyon and the Beare, will hereafter alſo (for ſo he may with <hi>Dauid, ex ante<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedentibus colligere conſequentia,</hi> from the by-paſt
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:14447:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>experiments of Gods prouidence towards him, gather what wil follow hereafter) reſcue him fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe vncircu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed <hi>Philiſtims</hi> that at any time riſe vp againſt him <note n="x" place="margin">1. Sam. 17.36</note>, and w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> hath crowned him here on earth with a corruptible crowne, will crowne him hereafter with a crowne incorruptible, and giue him a kingdome that cannot be ſhaken, reſerued in <hi>Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> to whom with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt be glory for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:14447:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
